# ABDULLAH AL MARUF

## SOFTWARE ENGINEER

# **I** LIFE PHILOSOPHY

"Do not fear failure but rather fear not trying"

- Roy T. Bennett

# CONTACT

- +1 (254) 715 0057
- aa.maruf.cse@gmail.com
- https://maruftuhin.com
- Waco, TX, USA

## EDUCATION

M.S. in Computer Science **Baylor University** Session 2020-Present

B.Sc. in Computer Science & Engineering Chittagong University of Engineering & Technology

Session 2012-2017

# TECHNICAL SKILLS





















MvSOL







Bash

# STRENGTHS

Team Work Self Learning

Communication Optimist

Problem Solving

## PROFILE

Passionate software engineer with 4 years of working experience in both developing Kubernetes tools in GO and managing microservice based infrastructure in production. Acted as team lead of AppsCode's KubeDB project for more than a year. Love to participate in programming contests. An enthusiastic team player.

#### EXPERIENCE -

# Graduate Research Assistant **Baylor Cloudhubs Lab**

📾 Jan. 2021 - Present

♥ Waco, TX, USA

- https://github.com/cloudhubs
- Performed telemetry log tracing analysis to reconstruct Microservices architecture.
- Performed static code analysis of java spring boot to detect JMS and Rest communication between Microservices.
- Technology Used: Java, Spring Boot, Docker, Docker Compose, Kubernetes.

# Intern Researcher

#### Red Hat Research

♥ Brno, CZ (Remote)

- https://research.redhat.com/
- > Led a small team of undergraduate students to conduct research on technical debt.
- Analyzed version controlled codebase to find probable code debts.
- Performed literature mapping study on technical debt and code smells.
- Technology Used: Java, Spring Boot, Git.

# DevOps Engineer **Digital Healthcare Solutions**

## Feb, 2020 - Dec, 2020

Dhaka, Bangladesh

https://dh.health

Formerly known as Telenor Health. DH makes high quality health services and health financing accessible for all.

- Concentrated on the migration of infrastructure to Kubernetes.
- > Experienced hybrid cloud infrastructure consisting of aws and openstack private cloud.
- Exercised cloud-native best practices for monitoring and alerting.
- Technology Used: AWS, Kubernetes, Ansible, Terraform, Docker, Docker Compose, Traefik, Nginx, HAProxy, Prometheus, etc.

# PROUD OF

#### Competitive Programming

- Solved 1100+ problems on different Online Judges.
- Divisional Champion of ACM ICPC Dhaka Regional '14 & '15

# Open Source Participation User, follower and contributor.

#### **KubeDB's growth**

From very few to thousands of daily users.

#### **iii** Leadership

Served as President of CUET COMPUTER CLUB. Also acted as Project Head of KubeDB.

# TOP OPEN SOURCE CONTRIBUTION

# kubernetes/kubernetes Production-Grade Container Orchestration.

#### kubedb

Database management tool for Kubernetes.

#### stash

Backup and restore plugin for Stash.

# kmodules/client-goKubernetes client-go utilities

# appscode/analytics Essential analytics for OSS

# Find me online

- in linkedin.com/in/maruftuhin
- github.com/the-redback
- stackoverflow.com/u/4628962
- twitter.com/maruf2hin
- https://maruftuhin.com
- codeforces.com/profile/ the\_redback

## EXPERIENCE

#### SOFTWARE ENGINEER

#### AppsCode Ltd.

■ May, 2017 - Jan, 2020P Dhaka, Bangladesh

Subsidiary company of AppsCode Inc. A platform for automate deployment, scaling, and management of containerized applications.

- Worked to build Kubernetes controller tools to utilize Kubernetes services.
- Maintenance and development of KubeDB project, A database management tool for Kubernetes.
- Led team members to design and implement the core features of KubeDB.
- Contributed and worked with many open source projects.
- Used: Go, Kubernetes, Docker, MongoDB, Elasticsearch, GCP, AWS, Azure.

# TOP PROJECTS

#### KubeDB

https://kubedb.com

A cloud-native database management solution for Kubernetes to simplify and automate provisioning, backup, recovery, failure detection for various popular databases.

- Led a small team to design & implement the core features.
- Designed and implemented various database support from scratch.
- Designed and implemented MongoDB clustering system support.
- Improved Postgresql and Elasticsearch clustering system.
- > Worked with Prometheus exporters to export database metrics.

#### Stash

https://appscode.com/products/stash

A volume backup tool designed for Kubernetes. Under the hood, it uses Restic for backup/restore purposes.

- Improved database backup system using stash.
- Designed and implemented Elasticsearch and MongoDB cluster backup system from scratch.
- > Integrated Stash support within Kubedb to backup/restore dbs.

#### BearMapping

A team-management project that uses machine learning to do an automatic literature review. It identifies relevant research papers that correspond to particular research questions.

- The backend was built with Java Spring Boot and Python, and the frontend was built with ReactJS.
- Followed cloud-native best practices to develop and deploy the microservices.

## Microservice Architecture (MSA) Reconstruction

- MSA reconstruction from tracing log.
- Used istio to collect the tracing log, JAVA to process it, and Graphviz to generate the architecture graph.